Guide to the William Howard Taft Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
William Howard Taft papers
1874-1928
MS 480
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
2
Miscellaneous letters by William Howard Taft, two speeches (one on strikes, the other on liberty under the law) and a colored pen and ink drawing by Sir Francis Carruthers Gould, entitled "Ex-President Taft in Retirement." Among the letters the most important was written to Colonel J.C. Hemphill from the White House, July 28, 1911 and discusses Senator Robert M. La Follette's attempt to introduce protectionist legislation on wool. In a number of letters in 1917 Taft writes to classmates of his Yale College class of 1878 to raise money for a special fund for their fortieth reunion. Also included are copies of notebooks of lectures and other teaching materials (1913-1916) kept while he was Kent Professor at the Yale Law School. A student essay, "The Third Term Question," circa 1874-1875 is included in the papers.
Taft, William H. (William Howard), 1857-1930
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Acquired by purchase and gift between 1940-1948, transferred from the Yale Law School, 1983.
Existence and Location of Copies
Notebooks of lectures and other teaching materials are available on microfilm (circa 600 frames on 1 reel, 35mm.) from Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library, at cost. Order no. HM131.
Existence and Location of Originals
Two ms. volumes (electrostatic copies) of case study notes, outlines and texts of lectures on constitutional law and government and other matters pertaining to the Yale Law School (1913-1916) date from the period when he served as Kent Professor in the Law School. The originals are in the Yale Law School Library.
Scope and Contents
These papers consist of a miscellaneous collection of items — letters, speeches and lecture notes — by William Howard Taft, acquired by purchase or gift between 1940 and 1948. Of the eighteen letters, seven were written while he was president of the United States. The most substantive of these is a letter dated July 28, 1911 which discusses Senator Robert M. LaFollette's attempt to introduce protectionist legislation on wool. Taft's lifelong interest in Yale University is shown in letters on nominees for honorary degrees, in letters concerning his sons when they were students at the College, and in a group of letters that he wrote to classmates in 1917 in preparation for the class's fortieth reunion.
The collection also includes two speeches, White House memorabilia and a sketch by Sir Francis Carruthers Gould, cartoonist for the Westminster Gazette, drawn on Taft's leaving office in 1914.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
Admitted to Ohio bar in 1880; practiced law in Cincinnati, 1883-1887; judge of Superior Court, Cinncinati, 1887-1890; solicitor general of U.S., 1890-1892; U.S. Circuit judge, 1892-1900; president, U.S. Philippines, 1900-1901; first civil governor of Philippines, 1901-1904; secretary of war, 1904-1908; 27th president of U.S., 1909-1913; professor of law, Yale University, 1913-1921; appointed chief justice of U.S., 1921.
Law; Tariff on wool; United States -- Politics and government; Educators; Lawyers; Politicians; Clarke, John Proctor, 1856-1932; Clemens, Cyril, 1902-1999; Coe, Henry C., 1856-1940; Coolidge, Calvin, 1872-1933; Day, George Parmly, 1876-1959; Gest, Clifford H.; Gould, F. Carruthers (Francis Carruthers), 1844-1925; Hemphill, John J. (John James), 1849-1912; Jewett, Carlton Rogers, 1852-1937; Jones, Frederick Scheetz, 1862-1944; King, Horatio C. (Horatio Collins), 1837-1918; La Follette, Robert M. (Robert Marion), 1855-1925; Law, William Henry, 1856-1915; Miller, George Douglas, 1847-1932; Olcott, Jacob Van Vechten, 1856-1940; Perry, Oliver Hazard, 1785-1819; Porter, Josephine Earl Sheffield, 1834-; Sickels, David Banks, 1837-1918; Taft, William H. (William Howard), 1857-1930; Wright, Henry Parks, 1839-1918; Yale College (1718-1887). Class of 1878; Yale Law School; Yale University -- Faculty; Yale University. Committee on Honorary Degrees
- Inventory
  - Letters from William Howard Taft to:
    - Clarke, John Proctor, 1856-1932, 1917 September 20 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Clemens, Cyril, 1902-, 1927 September 30 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Coe, Henry Clarke, 1856-1940, 1915 October 5, November 18 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Coolidge, [John] Calvin, Pres. U.S., 1872-1933, 1920 June 12 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Day, George Parmly, 1876-1959, 1908 June 30 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Gest, Clifford H., 1903 October 22 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Hemphill, John James, 1849-1912, 1911 July 28 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Jewett, Carlton Rogers, 1852-1937, 1917 August 31 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Jones, Frederick Sheetz, 1862-1944, 1914 September 22 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - King, Horatio Collins, 1837-1918, 1908 June 25 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Law, William Henry, 1856-1915, 1904 February 12, 1908 June 25, 1913 April 8, 1914 March 14 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Miller, George Douglas, 1847-1932, 1901 April 24, 1907 December 28 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Olcott, Jacob Van Vechten, 1856-1940, 1914 February 11 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Porter, Josephine (Sheffield), 1917 September 15 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Sickels, David Banks, 1837-1918, 1910 November 2 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Waldo and Marston, Messrs., [No year] November 22 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Henry Parks, 1838-1918, 1910 June 10 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Yale University. Committee on honorary degrees, 1910 November 24 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Manuscript, speech on strikes, 13 p., signed and dated on the last page, 1919 May 14 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - TM (copy) lecture, "Liberty under the law", [1928 May?] (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Printed cards for receptions at the White House, 1910, 1912 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Gould, Sir Francis Carruthers, 1844-1925, drawing of President Taft, [1914] (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Menu of a banquet to celebrate "Perry's victory centennial, 1813-1913..." with notes by Taft (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - "The Third Term Question"; Student Essay, Circa 1874-1875 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Two manuscript volumes (electrostatic copies) of case study notes, outlines and texts of lectures on constitutional law and government and other matters pertaining to Yale Law School
    Existence and Location of Originals
    Originals in Law School Library.
    - Volume I, 1913-1916 (Box 2)
    - Volume II, 1913-1916 (Box 3)
  - Folio. Honorary degree from the University of Cincinnati (Box 4)